Guide to the Samuel Clarke Pomeroy Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Samuel Clarke Pomeroy papers
1865-1895
MS 1196
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
Correspondence, legal and financial papers relating to Samuel Clarke Pomeroy's personal affairs and bribery charges brought against him in the U.S. Senate.
Pomeroy, S. C. (Samuel Clarke), 1816-1891
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated along with the Bowers Family Papers (MS 1194) by the Bowers family.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection is made up of subject files containing legal and financial papers of Samuel Clarke Pomeroy, as well as related correspondence. The earliest material consists of bills, receipts, letters, petitions, and other papers stemming from charges of bribery brought against Pomeroy after his reelection to the Senate in 1867 and again in 1873. The remaining subject files all deal with Pomeroy's involvement, as attorney, agent, or investor, in a variety of financial and legal affairs; these are detailed on the folder list which follows. Included in the files are correspondence, agreements, financial documents, and similar papers. The files are arranged chronologically.
These papers came to Yale University with the papers of Edward A. Bowers (Ms. Gr. No. 1194). There is one letter from Bowers in this collection, in folder 10; he appears to have been acting as Mrs. Pomeroy's attorney.
Biographical / Historical
Samuel Clarke Pomeroy was a Kansas Free-State advocate and U.S. Senator. He was born in Southampton, Massachusetts, on January 3, 1816. In 1842, he joined the Liberty Party and served in local Massachusetts offices. He moved to Kansas in 1854 and in 1856, became a delegate to first Republican National Convention. Between 1858 and 1859, he served as mayor of Atchison, Kansas. Pomeroy became the first U.S. Senator from Kansas. He opposed Lincoln in 1864, instead promoting Salmon Chase. In 1867 and again in 1873, he was reelected to Senate, but was then charged with bribery and forced to resign. In 1884, he was nominated for president by the American Prohibition National Convention. He died on August 27, 1891.
Business; Railroads; United States -- Politics and government; Lawyers; Legislators; Politicians; Pomeroy, S. C. (Samuel Clarke), 1816-1891; United States. Congress ( Expulsion); United States. Congress. Senate
- Inventory
  - Subject files
    - Settlement of bribery cases against Pomeroy, 1867-1875 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Compensation of Pomeroy as attorney for William McGarrahan, 1877, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Chiriqui Claim, Costa Rica, 1881, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Claims of the Choctaw Nation against the United States government, 1882-1883 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Denver and Eastern Railway and Coal Company, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Claims by La Abra Mining Company against the government of Mexico, 1884-1892, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Bill to erect a Timby tower to protect New York harbor, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - New Orleans, Baton Rouge, and Vicksburg Railroad Company, 1888, 1892, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Organization of the New Mausoleum Company, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Isthmian Pacific Railway Company (mainly correspondence from General S. C. Boynton), 1890-1895 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Bill on timber lands, [1893?] (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Contract for construction of the Central Branch of the Union Pacific Railroad, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)